<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on scverse</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/</link><description>Recent scverse news</description><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:00:05 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://scverse.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>scverse × BioContextAI: Community Infrastructure for Agentic Analysis</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-11-biocontextai/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:00:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-11-biocontextai/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="scverse--biocontextai-community-infrastructure-for-agentic-analysis"&gt;scverse × BioContextAI: Community Infrastructure for Agentic Analysis&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re excited to announce that we are partnering with &lt;a href="https://biocontext.ai/"&gt;BioContextAI&lt;/a&gt;, a new open-source initiative for building agentic systems in biomedical research.
BioContextAI provides a community registry for Model Context Protocol (MCP) servers.
These are standardized tools that allow AI systems to access specialized databases and software.
This project was recently published as a &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-025-02900-9"&gt;Nature Biotechnology correspondence&lt;/a&gt; and we are actively starting to explore and contribute scverse MCP servers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Improved i/o in anndata 0.12</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-anndata-012/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 10:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-anndata-012/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="012-released"&gt;0.12 released&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce that &lt;code&gt;anndata&lt;/code&gt; 0.12 is out now!
Check out &lt;a href="https://anndata.readthedocs.io/en/stable/release-notes/index.html#v0-12-0"&gt;the changelog&lt;/a&gt; for a full list of changes.
Here, we want to give our users a bit of a deep dive into the new functionality.
We have lots of great features, like zarr v3 support (package and format), full lazy loading, and new API customisability! Let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="zarr-v3"&gt;Zarr v3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zarr-specs.readthedocs.io/en/latest/v3/core/index.html"&gt;Zarr v3 as a file format&lt;/a&gt; provides improved cloud support, support for sharding to reduce the number of files created in a zarr store, and improved support for extensibility.
Check out the following graphic from the zarr docs:
By grouping chunks into shards, which are the individual file units, we can cut down the number of files a given zarr store has.
Compare this to zarr v2 where every chunk was its own file!
No more file system slowdowns, you can create large zarr stores with no concerns while still retaining the ease of use of zarr.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>scverse × Biomni: Agentic Single-Cell Analysis</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-07-biomni/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-07-biomni/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://scverse.org/img/blog/scverse_x_biomni_banner.png" style="max-width: 100%;" alt="scverse × Biomni partnership banner" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single-cell and spatial omics have unlocked unprecedented insights into cellular diversity, tissue architecture, and drug responses.
Despite the remarkable progress in computational tools, the diversity and complexity of analyses can still pose challenges.
While the scverse ecosystem provides powerful and interoperable tools such as &lt;a href="https://scanpy.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;Scanpy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://scvi-tools.org/"&gt;scvi-tools&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://squidpy.readthedocs.io/"&gt;Squidpy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://anndata.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;AnnData&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://mudata.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;MuData&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://spatialdata.scverse.org/en/latest/"&gt;SpatialData&lt;/a&gt;, researchers can sometimes face a steep learning curve, particularly when integrating multiple analytical steps or modalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;scverse&lt;/strong&gt; is a community-driven, open-source initiative behind many of the most widely adopted Python tools in single-cell biology, known for promoting modular, interoperable, and scalable analysis across diverse modalities—from transcriptomics to spatial and immune profiling.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Four new scverse core packages</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-core-expansion/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-core-expansion/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="four-new-core-packages-in-scverse"&gt;Four new core packages in scverse&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce that four new packages have joined the scverse core ecosystem: &lt;a href="https://github.com/scverse/snapatac2"&gt;SnapATAC2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/scverse/rapids_singlecell"&gt;rapids-singlecell&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/scverse/pertpy"&gt;pertpy&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/scverse/decoupler"&gt;decoupler&lt;/a&gt;.
This broadens the scope of scverse beyond our so far supported modalities and brings in new functionality for epigenomics, perturbation screens, GPU acceleration, and functional inference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single-cell analysis is evolving rapidly, with new experimental modalities and larger datasets becoming the norm.
To keep up with this, we’re expanding scverse to support more domains, more data types, and more scalable computing backends.
By bringing these mature, well-maintained tools into the core, we aim to provide a consistent and interoperable foundation across all stages of single-cell analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Highlights from the inaugural scverse conference</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/2024-conference-summary/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://scverse.org/blog/2024-conference-summary/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://scverse.org/img/blog/conference2024.png" style="max-width: 100%;" alt="Group photo from the scverse conference" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first scverse conference, held in Munich, Germany from 10-12 September, 2024 brought together leading scientists, developers, and researchers from the single-cell genomics and spatial biology community. The conference was organized around five main events: (A) 6 keynotes from leaders in the field (B) 13 short talks from developers, graduate students, postdocs (C) 14 workshops with hands-on experience on various aspects of data analysis and software development (D) Poster session showcasing more than 50 posters (E) Talks from our sponsors showcasing their latest advancements. This year, the focus was on latest community-driven developments in multi-modal and spatial data analysis, broadening scverse accessibility and outreach, and enhancing interoperability. With over 170 participants from 17 different countries, the inaugural scverse conference was a success. Here, we provide major highlights from the conference.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hello world</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 00:00:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://scverse.org/blog/hello-world/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Due to the increasing reliance of scientific research on complex computational pipelines, foundational software in the life sciences has outgrown individual labs and institutes in terms of its scale and impact.
This has motivated us to start something more than a code repository for an exciting new project – a new consortium to organize and support core (mostly) Python tools for single cell life science research.
We are excited to announce &lt;strong&gt;scverse&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>