<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on scverse</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/</link><description>Recent scverse news</description><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:05 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://scverse.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Four new scverse core packages</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-core-expansion/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://scverse.org/blog/2025-core-expansion/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="four-new-core-packages-in-scverse">Four new core packages in scverse&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce that four new packages have joined the scverse core ecosystem: &lt;a href="https://github.com/scverse/snapatac2">SnapATAC2&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/scverse/rapids_singlecell">rapids-singlecell&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/scverse/pertpy">pertpy&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/scverse/decoupler">decoupler&lt;/a>.
This broadens the scope of scverse beyond our so far supported modalities and brings in new functionality for epigenomics, perturbation screens, GPU acceleration, and functional inference.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Single-cell analysis is evolving rapidly, with new experimental modalities and larger datasets becoming the norm.
To keep up with this, we’re expanding scverse to support more domains, more data types, and more scalable computing backends.
By bringing these mature, well-maintained tools into the core, we aim to provide a consistent and interoperable foundation across all stages of single-cell analysis.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Highlights from the inaugural scverse conference</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/2024-conference-summary/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://scverse.org/blog/2024-conference-summary/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://scverse.org/img/blog/conference2024.png" style="max-width: 100%;" alt="Group photo from the scverse conference" />
&lt;p>The first scverse conference, held in Munich, Germany from 10-12 September, 2024 brought together leading scientists, developers, and researchers from the single-cell genomics and spatial biology community. The conference was organized around five main events: (A) 6 keynotes from leaders in the field (B) 13 short talks from developers, graduate students, postdocs (C) 14 workshops with hands-on experience on various aspects of data analysis and software development (D) Poster session showcasing more than 50 posters (E) Talks from our sponsors showcasing their latest advancements. This year, the focus was on latest community-driven developments in multi-modal and spatial data analysis, broadening scverse accessibility and outreach, and enhancing interoperability. With over 170 participants from 17 different countries, the inaugural scverse conference was a success. Here, we provide major highlights from the conference.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hello world</title><link>https://scverse.org/blog/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 00:00:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://scverse.org/blog/hello-world/</guid><description>&lt;p>Due to the increasing reliance of scientific research on complex computational pipelines, foundational software in the life sciences has outgrown individual labs and institutes in terms of its scale and impact.
This has motivated us to start something more than a code repository for an exciting new project – a new consortium to organize and support core (mostly) Python tools for single cell life science research.
We are excited to announce &lt;strong>scverse&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>